He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall,
and he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him,
and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
In our time
many year into break free of the prison of a flat secular materialism to see and to know reality
as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate
everyday life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen
Damick and Father Stephen De Young host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation.
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, giant killers and dry casters.
You are listening to the Lord of Spirits
podcast, My Co-host, Father Stephen D'Yan,
is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana.
And I'm Father Andrew Stephen D'Amick
in Emmaus, Pennsylvania.
This is a pre-recorded episode.
So we're not taking any calls this time.
And even though I said I'm in Emmaus
and other Siemens, Louisiana, the truth is.
When you're hearing this
Assuming you're listening to it live. We're actually both somewhere in Texas
Can't tell you where exactly but some not listening to it live listening to the premiere. That's that's true
Yes, thank you for that precision. Yeah, and also we we will take your call if you sense
That we're recording and you call right now. It's true
It's not what I'm really hoping by repeating that these pre-recorded episodes
is that listeners of the show.
will just start calling the ancient faith studios at odd hours.
Poor Trudy.
Hoping to catch us recording. That's what I'm going for.
Are they on now? Can I get through?
Yeah.
So a brief commercial.
So on October 26 to 29, 2023, Happy New Year, by the way.
At the Antiochian Village in Western Pennsylvania, the forests of Penn,
We are going to be holding the...
first ever Lord of Spirits Conference. Father Steven and I are going to both be there,
we'll both be speaking as well as will be Archbishop Alexander Galitson and Father's David
Subu and Lucas Christensen, and yes there will be an RPG tournament. Don't let them drag. Extra
points to anyone, and I'm not kidding about this. Extra points to anyone who brings me a copy of
jack chicks, literary and yes indeed.
film classic, Dark Dungeons.
The schedule is still being worked on,
but you can find all the current details
and you can register very important
because like we've sold out, I think,
over half the anti-occur village now, well over half,
well over half, yeah.
You can go to store.antianfaith.com slash events.
So get your tickets right now.
And because my sister had to have this question answered,
answered.
question being and I quote, can I get a refund if somebody dies before then?
You mean like you could be.
I mean, even if you're I don't know, I could die.
You could sell someone else could.
I think I think they would still hold the event.
We'd have to all.
Yes, yes.
But the answer is yes.
Yes, it is possible.
There are.
We get a refund up to some point.
I don't know when exactly.
So, but yes, it is a thing. It is a thing. So the other commercial I want to give, since, you know,
this is our bully pulpit. I want to point everyone that you are a bully. And I am sometimes a bully.
But I'm a nice bully. I'm a very nice bully. I want to point everyone to a newly released
pilgrimage documentary that has begun to be available through ancient faith radio and, of course,
on all of your favorite podcasting apps. It is called
the wolf and the cross.
And it is the result of a pilgrimage
that friend of this show, I shouldn't call him that,
actual friend, Richard Roland.
And I took along with my daughter to Lithuania this past summer
and we took a made a bunch of recordings
and we've done a huge amount of research.
The first episode is out.
It's a little over two hours long.
Fans of this show should recognize
that it's a very short episode of something.
and uh...
very very high level of production. We've got ambient music, we've got sound effects, we've got voice actors.
It is not just the whole nine yards. This goes to 10 yards. This is 10 yards worth of material.
So I hope everyone will check that out. Like I said, the first episode is now available. We're planning on releasing them about
once a month or so. Maybe have some bonus episodes on top of the nine main episodes that we're planning on doing.
I think you
find it fascinating and a lot of fun to listen to actually. So tonight though.
And allow me to point out, point it out.
The shameless self-promotion is over, that when I called out Richard Rollins, he fled the
country. That is actually true.
Yes, so.
Yeah, he'd never even been outside of the country.
He's got to be.
Yeah, yeah.
So tonight though for this episode we're gonna be talking about
confession. We're continuing our series on sacraments, confession is the Christian
sacrament of the forgiveness of sins. What exactly is it? What does it do? Before
we get to that though, we really need to ask, what is forgiveness? So is it true?
I've heard this. Is it true that some Christians actually think that God can't
Forgive people?
Kind of true.
Right, they wouldn't say that.
We should be, you know, fair and say they would not say that.
But what does that kind of mean?
Well, part of what occasion this phrasing was the exerting from a YouTube conversation
I had by a person who I believe is a Muslim apologist, okay?
a less than a minute long clip.
of me saying that God can forgive people.
And this was posted as me making,
me as a Christian priest making a startling admission.
You've given away the farm.
It was admits, right?
Like admits.
Like I've been trying to conceal this for people
that God can forgive people.
Wow.
Right.
Um...
But what occasion this from him, I'm assuming,
I don't know him, but what I believe occasion this from him
and from some other folks and other interactions I've seen,
and what occasion be talking about it
in the YouTube conversation was that the people involved
had been speaking to certain Christians
who hold to
a certain view of from their perspective they would say how forgiveness works.
Right. Okay. So they wouldn't say God can't forgive sins. Right. Right. Right. But the way
they would define, theologically define God forgiving sins to especially non-
Christians does not sound like forgiveness. And here's what I
mean by that. There is and we got to be honest, this is mostly some of not all by any means,
but some of our Protestant friends. Have this view that God has to punish sin. Right. And
not just in general, right?
Yeah, all same.
But then he asked to punish sins.
Right, right, right.
right? Right? Like the individual acts all have to be punished because if he doesn't punish
every single sin then he isn't just. God isn't righteous. He isn't just if he fails to fully
punish any sin. Right. And so there are a lot of problems with this idea. Yeah. I mean,
like logical, biblical. Right. I mean, to me, the biggest one is this sense that God must do
something. Yeah. Yeah. That God is subject to some kind of necessity. Right. That there's
that there's, I mean, frankly, that there's something that God has to be obedient to.
Right. Right. That for God to be just, he has to do this means that this category of justice
or righteousness is somehow over above him.
Yeah, I mean, ancient people would have regarded something like that as being a God itself.
Right.
So if that's true, then whatever that is or whoever put it in place is the actual God,
right?
Yeah.
So that's a problem.
Right.
But when the folks who hold this view, when you ask them, obviously...
They're not going to say that right say no no no no no there's something above God. Yeah, this is just who God is right right?
It's God's own nature
Right God's own nature God has to be true to his nature again
Using has to is weird in that case with nature right because nature is just who and what you are right but
God acts consistently which is nature
But that
ends up amounting to a weird circular reasoning, right? So it's like God is
God is just and therefore he has to punish every sin completely. Yeah. I mean
that's about one particular version of justice, right? Right. Yeah. Right. They
would say, well that particular version of justice is God's nature, but that's
That's why it becomes a weird circular argument.
Let's say
for the sake of argument that God actually didn't have to punish any sins and all, right?
Let's say God just forgave all sins, right? And he didn't have to punish any of them, right?
Then that would be the way God is, and so that would be justice.
Right. It's just a definitional argument. It's really what it is.
So you know, that's the way God is because that's the way God is, right, is not an argument, right?
It's just a statement.
Yeah.
It's a topology, right?
Well, the first rule of topology club is the first rule of topology club.
Yes.
So the,
you could use that same argument for any, to support any notion of God's justice.
Right.
That's who he is.
But so beyond those logical issues, right, is the fact that you end up with a God, then
who is merciless.
Yeah.
Because how can he, if he has to punish?
Definitionally, one of the words, not the most common one, they probably the second most
common word.
in the New Testament that gets translated as mercy.
The literal lexical definition is not punishing
to the full extent.
Hm.
Right?
So if a judge could sentence you to,
I mean, I'm using a modern example,
but if he could sentence you to 20 years in prison,
and he sentences you to 10, he is having mercy in that sense.
Right right by by not punishing your Philipses Philips debt
so that
Defend that word for mercy
God can't have in this view at all
Right right and
And the way that other term then gets interpreted
According to this view is well, yes God has to punish every sin and he has to punish it fully
But so he shows mercy to you
Bye.
punishing someone else, namely Christ for it. So in order to argue that God is just, because justice
has been defined as punishing every sin completely. And so to make God fit that definition, you now have
him letting a guilty person go free and punishing an innocent person and saying
that makes him both just and merciful.
Right. I mean, I can imagine.
But really, it kind of makes him neither.
Yeah. Say, I can imagine, you know, my kids occasionally
get in fights and occasionally do wrong things.
Are they fighting about like etymologies?
Not today.
No.
Okay.
But we do, I mean, it is my house.
So, occasionally, we do have conversations about, yeah.
Yeah.
Um, but
But, you know, if one of them, like, let's say one of them decides to,
like, I have a fondness for what we refer to in my house, simply as fake cheese, which is that sort of
chemically produced tostitos, nacho cheese, you know. And I bring at home usually expecting that I will
eat some of it. Sometimes when I go to eat some of it, it is gone, already gone, you know,
someone has taken it without permission. So if I find out who took it without permission,
I say, we'll look.
I'm going to have mercy on you by punishing your brother instead.
You know, he has to go to his room for the rest of the day or he's, you know, grounded from
playing with his friends. Number one, they would be dumbfounded, right? But number two,
I mean, that would seem so arbitrary and like cruel, especially to the person who had to receive
the punishment. You know, and probably the person who didn't receive it, the kid would be like,
just got to confuse by the
whole thing. You know, yeah, when his turn was going to be. Yeah, right. When are you
going to get it, you know, next time? Yeah, I mean, it's not merciful because, you know,
there's no like like in that model where to be merciful is not to give the full punishment.
That's not what's actually happening there. What's happening is well, part of the punishment
or all of it is being given to someone else instead, you know, the holding back is not
actually a thing within this model that we're talking about.
Right.
You know?
So the scriptures are pretty clear
that the God who created the heavens of the earth
at least is not merciless.
In fact, quite the opposite.
Right.
And wave is abundant and plentious in mercy.
Yeah, way more merciful than any human being ever.
Right.
And that creates yet another problem with that view,
which is when we're told by Christ,
forgive as the Lord forgave you.
Whoa.
I just thought, yeah.
Yeah.
What does that mean?
Yeah, that means the scenario in which I punish
I get it and do everything, right?
Not the one who does something.
Right.
Or does it just mean as any of the folks who hold that
view and say when it comes to humans, right, they would say,
well, no, you need to just forgive people.
Yeah, I mean, you don't need to punish every sin committed
against you completely.
Yeah.
Just let it go.
just say
It didn't move on.
It didn't happen.
Move on, right?
Right.
Have more love in you for them than the pain they caused you.
Right?
That's what we would say.
But, um, so are humans more merciful than God?
Yeah.
In that model, humans can do that but God can't.
Right.
And if you're going to say God can't do that because it would be unjust,
demanding us to be unjust?
Yeah. Right? So the whole thing kind of falls apart. Right? That whole understanding.
And so the truth is, as shocking as it is apparently to at least one Muslim
apologist, God can and does and always has just forgiven people their sins. Yeah.
Now the rest of this episode...
We're going to be kind of talking about how he has done that,
at different times, at different places,
and how he does that today, and who is involved.
We talked about last time in the ordination episode.
God works through people, through whom does God do this.
That's what we're going to be talking about the rest of the episode.
But we have to start with forgiveness is a thing.
Yeah. Forgiveness is a thing. And it's not, again, a question of what sins was Christ
punished for 2,000 years ago. Brief note to our Protestant listeners who are not Calvin
how does that even work for you?
Like I get how it works for a Calvinist, right?
Because God had already decided who he was going to save and who he wasn't.
So Christ was punished for the sins of those people he was going to save and not for the others.
But for the rest of you folks, who are Calvinists?
Right? Like how does that work?
How does that work?
Anyway.
I'll leave that to you.
Or we can sort of abandon that view of atonement and sin
and punishment.
And our lives get much better.
So the other piece that we kind of need
to talk about here at the beginning
is about the Torah, the law as Saint Jerome would have it.
Although when he trans.
lady at that way. I think we've talked about this in a previous episode that when he translated
it that way, it didn't happen with the same connotation as Lex did not have the same connotation
as Law does today. Yeah, right. It's much more like ways.
Right. Yeah. Like teaching. Yeah. Yeah. Teachings. Yeah. Custom. Yeah. Way of life. But so. And I hate
you know how I hate to pick on people.
really so I hate to be seen to be picking on people
Right because you know, hey
Thursemicus kind of had it right, you know as long as you appear just you can act unjust and get the best of both worlds
But
Well goodnight everybody
Many of the same folks who hold to
the view of sort of justice right and and
and the pun-
of sin and forgiveness that we just talked about also have another belief regarding the Torah,
the law, right, the commandments, in terms of what it's for, right, what the purpose was. And
that's why it's germane here when we're talking about confession and forgiveness. And that's that
the view that
some folks have is that the commandments are outlying away to earn your way to have it.
Yeah, right.
And I think that this is mostly connected with our dispensationalist friends, where there's a lot of folks.
Yeah, definitely them, but also others.
Yeah, especially gets out into a lot of other groups as well.
there's this notion that well
God set up this one method of salvation that he knew everyone was going to fail at.
So that, you know, the next method of salvation is going to come on the scene with Jesus.
And you know, you don't have to do much for that one.
And it's okay.
You know, it's not about you failing or succeeding.
Jesus is going to take care of it, essentially, right?
Right.
This is the view I was raised with, it's even jellical, even though we...
weren't especially dispensationalist. Right. And classical reform, like we're not just
reformed like Calvinist, but reformation Protestantism is that Christ comes and fulfills the
law and earns. It's the flip side of what we were just talking about. Right. Christ earns heaven
for himself.
Yeah, so he gets it all and now he can kind of hand it out.
The Torah perfectly.
And so he receives the punishment for our sins,
and he gives us the heaven that he earned.
Yeah.
Almost like it's for the storehouse of merit.
And so the core problem here is
that's never what the Torah, the law, the commandments,
that's never what they were.
Yeah, never says that anywhere in the Old Testament.
It says that nowhere in the Old Testament.
says that nowhere in the New Testament.
Jewish people have never believed that.
They didn't believe in in ancient Israel, they didn't believe in the second
temple period. I have an obf very good authority, they don't believe in now.
Yeah, and even, I mean, that's why even there are some, some Jewish people who don't
actually believe in an afterlife.
In heaven.
It's her life, the resurrection.
Right. Which would be an impossible belief to hold if that's what the law was all about.
Right.
But yeah.
or salvation however you wanted to find out about earning salvation is not about
earning anything right and there's all kinds of basic levels that falls apart
beyond the fact that it literally never says that and as we're going to talk
about here in a minute it says the scriptures say it was for something else.
I mean just think for a second about the fact that most of the commandments of
the Torah are directed at Israelites.
and only Israelites.
Yeah.
Right?
So, is it just way harder for Jewish people to get to heaven that everybody else, right?
Like, is there a road of salvation just like way harder than everyone else's?
Right? Gentiles just have to not eat blood and
refrain from sexual immorality and idolatry.
Yeah, because I mean the law includes commandments for them.
Yeah.
But that's about all you have to do, right?
You can eat bacon?
You can...
right? You can live laugh love. But you know, so at that level, it doesn't make sense either.
But more importantly, the scriptures tell us what the commandments of the Torah were for,
right? And R4 still, right? And that's that they operated as a sort of sin management system.
Right. Right.
The only God of Israel comes to dwell among his people.
He is holy. Therefore that is dangerous because they are sinners. And so the
torsus system for managing the sins of the people. Part of that system is
giving commandments of life, right? Meaning here's how to live your life to avoid
sin, right? To avoid coming under the power of sin. Part of that then also though
is what you do
when you sin, how you deal with sin when it happens.
Yeah, I mean, some of the commandments are like you can't keep all the commandments without
breaking some of the commandments.
Right.
There's just around it.
St. Paul says this in Galatians, when he says the law was added because of transgressions.
Yeah.
Right.
The Torah was given because of transgressions.
If we were not for sin, it wouldn't have been...
been needed. Right? Well, that means it can't be about how to earn your way to eternal life
or salvation. Right? So yeah, keeping Torah, the idea of keeping Torah is not just about not
doing a whole list of bad things. Yeah, that's a small portion. Yeah, I think a lot of people
that their concept of it is, you know, thou shalt not.
that's showed not, that's showed not, and as long as you shout not, terrible grammar
right now. But as long as you shout not, then you've got it covered, right? And like,
oh, you broke one. Sorry. That's it. Big loser. Now you're going to hell. Right? Right?
I think there's nothing you can do about it. Yeah. Unless someone gets punished for that
thing you did right right and again that's nowhere in Scripture and what
One of the things that really highlights this is that the Scriptures say that there are
a bunch of people who kept the Torah perfectly.
And even though they kept the Torah perfectly, they still needed Christ.
They still needed a Savior.
So for example, one of these that people find surprising is David.
Yeah, the adulterer and murderer?
Yes
Right? And if you want to see where, right, you go to where, after the kingdom has been,
most of the kingdom has been taken away from Solomon because of his sins, right? So,
Reabome becomes the king of Judah, which covers, you know, Judah, Benjamin, and most of the Levites.
Right. And then the other tribes, the northern kingdom of Israel,
is
being given to Jeroboam, son of Nebath, who is one of Solomon's court officials. And God
sends the prophet to Jeroboam and the prophet says to Jeroboam, if you keep all of my commandments
and my statutes just as my servant David did, I will also give you an everlasting dynasty.
Right.
And so, right.
little record scratch David perfectly kept all of his commandments and
statutes right well he did once you realize the fact that right a whole bunch of
those commandments and statutes are about what to do when you sin yeah yep so
when David sinned he repented he did what the Torah prescribed right he did what
he was called to do.
Right. And so he is as far as God's Torah is concerned, right? He had kept it perfectly.
That didn't mean never sinning it, but doing what it said when I said, and by the way, by the way,
I know there's this weird meme going around that's come out of certain old testament scholarly
circles that the Torah only offered forgiveness for us.
unintentional sins.
Here's an example where that's obviously false.
David committing adultery in murder
was not unintentional or accidental or involuntary.
Right.
Okay. And how do you involuntarily steal?
Right. Right.
Okay. Anyway.
Oops, I robbed someone.
So anyway, but so David kept the Torah perfectly, still needed a savior.
Yep, right. Some unnamed Gentiles kept the Torah. You can find that in Romans 2
verse 14 specifically, but in Romans chapter 2, in Romans chapter 1, I'll back up even a little further.
briefly. So St. Paul writes his epistle to the Romans to the Christian community in Rome,
after for a couple of years the emperor Claudius had expelled all of the Jews from Rome.
And this is actually mentioned in the book of Acts. This is how St. Paul ended up meeting Saint
Priscilla and Aquila is that they were
some of the Jewish people who had been exiled from Rome.
And then after a couple of years he let them come back.
And so the Christian church with only Gentile members had continued functioning in Rome.
And now the Jewish members are coming back after being away for this time.
And so St. Paul writes, the epistle of the Romans aimed at primarily helping them reintegrate.
Right.
one community and not becoming these two separate. This is a constant struggle for St. Paul is he doesn't
want there to be a Jewish church over here and a Gentile church over there, right sort of ethnically
defined, right? And so then the first chapter of Romans, St. Paul is kind of talking to the Gentile
members of the church talking about all the former wickedness and depravity they were involved in.
back when they were pagans. But then in the second chapter, he turns to the Jewish Christians
and says, well, okay, yeah, you weren't in the same boat, right? You had received the Torah,
you had received the Covenant, the Commandments, right? You had received these things. But
then he turns around and says, okay, you received all these things, you received the Torah, but
did you keep it? Did you really live by it? Or did you violate it? Right? And as part
of that.
argument, right? He says, you know, the Gentiles, these people who aren't Jewish, there's
a bunch of them who have kept what's required of them in the Torah, without knowing about
the Torah. And he says they were like a law unto themselves. They were like a Torah themselves.
They were self-taught, if Torah means teachings, right? They're sort of self-taught. They
kept those things better than some of you did who...
Read and studied it
right
But so in the course of that argument and in the point that he's trying to make St. Paul says there were Gentiles who didn't even know what the Torah was didn't know the law
But who kept it
He's not saying by that well, I guess those Gentiles have earned their way
Earned their salvation and don't need Christ right that's not what say Paul is saying right again see chapter 1
One.
But his point is, again, about Torah keeping.
But probably the most important example here, I think, is in Philippians chapter 3.
And say...
Paul in sort of lifting off his credentials from his former life as a non-Christian Pharisee.
If Libyan 36 says that he, this is before the road to Damascus,
say Paul's writing after but saying about himself before that he was blameless in terms of the law.
He was blameless in terms of the Torah. Yeah, which he's not saying he never sinned.
And he certainly not saying he does not need to save you.
Yes, because he goes on to say he was murdering Christians.
Yeah, right.
Yeah.
Right.
So, and he certainly is to say, in fact, he goes on to say that he counts all of that as
rubbish, as garbage, compared to what he found in Christ.
Right.
Because what you get from the law is not the same thing that you get from Jesus Christ.
So because it serves a different function,
there's a whole different thing, right?
Then what Christ does.
And so, something, some of that up is that
the commandment to repent is a commandment.
So, you can't say you've kept all the commandments
unless you also have kept the commandment to repent.
and you can't repent in the
you've sinned. Right. So and the person who repents is keeping the commandments. Right. Yep.
Which I mean, you know, as a sidebar, right? Some Christians have this notion of Christian life
is about not committing any sins. But, you know, you're gonna sin. Like, there's just, it's just
just the way that it is. Sorry everybody.
You're going to sin. And sure, we try to not to commit sins, but the Christian life,
a lot of it actually is what do you do when you sin? And doing that does not make you a bad Christian.
It makes you a Christian. That's what being a Christian is about is about this life of repentance.
So as a sidebar, although, you know, again, not about earning salvation either, but we'll get to that.
it's a sub-
But yeah, and it also frankly this idea that that
God gave a bunch of rules to the Israelites that he knew they would never be able to keep just to make a point
right right
Like you could kind of make that work in this a lot of times theological discussions
End up in this weird abstract place
This weird ideological place where it's just sort of ideas.
is battling against each other.
And if you try and put them into the real world,
you quickly realize that the whole conversation
makes no sense.
Yeah, and I mean, this is one of the polemics
sometimes that ex-Christians particularly have
against Christianity is like, well,
God set up all these rules that he knew
that no one could follow, and now he sends us to hell
for not following them.
And you know, if that's you, listener,
if you think that that's what Christianity is,
I don't believe in that either.
You know?
Right.
So over against this idea that like
Israel was a giant fallout vault, right? Is the right? What you're saying when you say that?
Right? When someone says that, right? And you look at this abstract idea, you say, well, yeah,
I know it's really hard for me. I mean, I sin. So yeah, that seems to make sense to me.
Okay, but let's take it outside the realm of ideas. Let's take this into the world of,
We'll say
again because I don't want to argue about it, 1500 years of history.
1500 years of actual humans, okay?
Of humans being butchered and slaved, disemboweled, taken into exile, right?
As judgment for having not kept rules that God gave them that he knew they couldn't keep.
Yeah.
That's what you're saying, right?
That's the God you're talking about.
Because that's what happens to Israel.
And right, yeah.
All to make a point.
That point being, oh you Gentiles, you should just believe in Jesus and not try to keep
commandments.
This is Bizarro World when you take it outside the realm of ideas.
When you take it outside of a theology textbook, right, it doesn't make sense.
And so, you know, and the bigger problem is then people try to structure their actual
lives according to a set of ideas that don't make sense in the real world.
which is not something God is ever...
called us to do. Right. So when God gave the Torah, the world was already full of
violence. It was full of vengeance taking. It was full of consequences of sin and
wickedness playing out in people's lives and destroying them. Okay. The Torah
doesn't bring that into the world. Right?
The Torah comes into the world in order to bring forgiveness in order to bring the presence
of God into the world safely for the people in whose midst he's living.
It is, as St. John says in the prologue to his gospel.
The law came through Moses, grace and truth came through Jesus Christ.
we have.
receive grace after grace. The law is grace. The Torah is grace. It is not the opposite.
Yeah, because grace is the action of God in this world. And that comes from God. It is his act.
And there are other things going on through the Torah too, right? Because the Torah is a way to
practice holiness and it's a way to live and be
the world goes listen again to our blessings and curses episode right where you have a life
in this world that is blessed rather than cursed and that is not rewarded versus punished.
Yeah right this is this is consequences. Yeah it's like it's like keeping a garden you know if you
plant the particular plants that you have on the right way and water them in the right way
and take
care of them in the right way, they're going to do well. But if you neglect them or you
plant them too close together or you put it next to something you shouldn't have or water
it too much or not enough, then it's going to do badly. It's not that God is saying,
ah, I see what you're doing. I will smite your vegetables. This is what happens when
you live in a certain way. Yeah. Yeah. And all of these things were still wrong.
for the Torah. Yeah, yeah, sin wasn't invented by the Torah. Yes. Right. God had not said
thou shalt not murder before King killed Abel. It was still murder. Yeah. It wasn't God
saying it that made it a sin. Right. It wasn't God saying it that made it evil. It's sort
of it wasn't God saying it that gave it consequences. Yeah, it's sort of written into the fabric
of creation itself.
Right.
Yeah.
That's why you can't reveal it.
That's why you can't just revise morality, by the way.
Right. Right.
And so the Torah is teaching.
It's got revealing that, making that plane to people.
Right?
The law is given, as our liturgy says,
as an aid, as a guide to aid us.
Right?
Instead of being in the dark, like the Gentiles
fumbling around, trying to figure out
where I live, like, is-
Here's how to live in the world in a state of blessedness.
That's a help.
That's a good thing.
And the whole wisdom literature tradition, both inside and outside of the Old Testament
scriptures, is based on meditating on that, on working that out in various practical ways
in human lives.
So the other thing.
that we've been hinting at already is that salvation is not, and we've talked about this
a lot when we've talked about theosis before, but salvation is not just having your sins
forgiven.
Yeah.
And not returning to a state of innocence.
Nor is it just, I get to go to heaven when I die instead of going to hell.
Yeah.
Salvation is again it's the osu- Salvation is
coming like God, which is what humanity was created to do before sin came into the world.
Yeah, I mean, the first commandments that God gave to cultivate the earth and to fill it,
are exactly the things that he himself had just been doing in Genesis 1.
So he's saying, right, these are the works I did.
I want you to continue my works, become more like me.
And then as now, sin is obviously an obstacle to that.
Yeah right.
Right.
But it's an obstacle along a road that we're still walking that's going in a positive direction.
And that is salvation that's accomplished in Christ.
Which the law was never set up for through his incarnation, through his death and resurrection.
Right his death and resurrection is removing another one of those obstacles death, right?
but
Christ removes all the obstacles, but he also fulfills the path that leads to God.
So all of that lengthy throat clearing.
So what exactly is forgiveness then?
Forgiveness is just forgetting about stuff.
No.
So, when forgiveness is talked about in the Scriptures, it is talked about in the context
of purification, purified of uncleanness.
Uncleanness.
Yeah.
Right.
Uncleanness over and over again, starting in the Torah is paralleled with, right?
It wasn't just that God was super concerned about mildew.
I love that example every time.
I'm sorry to have an ugly bathroom.
It's not that you're super concerned about mildew.
This mildew represents something.
It's not that the skin condition is called leprosy or like the worst diseases.
It's that it's an image of how sin works.
Well, I think for instance about first John 1.9, very famous verse
where it says that if we confess our sins that God...
is faithful and just he's gonna, and these are paired together, forgive us our sins and cleanse
us from all unrighteousness. So there's that purification as part of the whole action. Right, or Psalm 51,
which is 50 in the Greek numbering. Cleans me with this, but actually we clean. Yeah, right.
Wash me and actually be wider than snow. Right, so this is over and over and over and over again.
Right, that your Sinsby is Scarlet. I mean, it just yeah.
This washing connection goes along with forgiveness of sins everywhere.
Yeah. Yeah.
And you notice what that isn't.
Right.
This isn't about crime and punishment.
This is about purification because as we said before many times,
there's your sin at sinning committing sins.
Right.
And sin does something to you.
It changes you.
Right and that needs to be
healed and corrected. But so today's word of the day, so anytime you hear it, scream
real loud. Wow. That's a throat.
It is. Is August. You probably won't hear it that well, you'll hear it a few times in
this episode, but beyond that, I don't know how many times you'll hear it. But as a kid,
I actually did that.
You actually, the rest of the day I would scream at my parents.
The screamer allowed after you watch.
Yeah.
Peebe's oh yes.
In restaurants.
It didn't matter.
Wow.
I'm sure everyone else was watching it
so they understood what you were doing.
Probably not.
I tried to lead my younger sister into my same evils
and indignities by screaming along with me.
Anyway, August is a Greek word.
not to be confused with ios, although they're spelled very similarly.
Yeah, there's one letter means holy. One iota's difference.
Yes.
Anyway, they are not...
I'm going to go ahead and say they are not
etymologically related. Yeah. There are a couple guys who argue they are
but I don't think they are.
uh
So this word has several usages, right, because, of course, meaning is derived from usage.
With words.
One of them is awe or reverence or fear.
Okay.
And this is in the fear of the Lord, the sense.
The fear of the Lord, the beginning of wisdom, all that or stuff.
Or in the liturgy when we talk about the dread mysteries of Christ.
Yes, right?
that we're not talking about scary or macabre.
Right, we're talking about it.
Um, this kind of sense of awe or reverence, right?
Um, it can also mean impurity or uncleanness.
Yeah, right.
So like it seems like, it's like English word mullet,
which can mean so many different things.
Um, mostly means a sweet haircut.
It's don't seem to have much to do with each other.
I mean, the-
initial blush, right? Okay, all reverence and fear. Okay. And then impurity
or uncleanness. Like, but what's the relationship between his concepts? If you are
impure or unclean, then the appropriate attitude for you to have as you approach God is all
reverence fear. Right. So that's what it's still that. Yeah, it's connected
together. Yeah. Think of Isaiah during his vision.
Yeah, man of unclean lips.
Right.
And the third use is related to the second one.
And that's an abomination.
It's the word that you translate the word abomination.
You're really like a thing that's thrown out or cast away or, you know, yeah, yeah.
Polluted thing.
Yeah.
Um, and then it can also be reused to refer to a sin offering type of sacrifice.
Right yeah the the sacrificial ritual that seemed
to sort of remove the impurity and uncleanness.
Yeah, there's kind of this whole sort of network
of meanings that all used it various ways
with this one word.
Right.
Probably the most common place it shows up
is in second temple Jewish literature,
and a vast swath of it.
It's the word in Greek that's used to talk about impurity,
both ritual impurity in terms of the Torah
and moral impurity.
Right.
And once you understand that concept and the conceptual link in this word, it helps you understand a lot of
texts, right, in a new way
In the scripture like the fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom
Yeah, I mean you can not about don't be an atheist or you can't know anything, right?
No, I mean it's it's and I mean the cool thing is is you can kind of
use a few of these different meanings there. So all reverence, fear. Okay, so you
know that sense of approaching God reverentially, but also, you know, the
repentant act of sin offering and sacrifice is the beginning of wisdom. So that
is, yes, repentance. Yeah. The idea of repentance being the beginning of wisdom.
Right. Right. Yeah. I mean, the kind of humility being the beginning of wisdom.
Yeah.
I mean, I'm reminded, I think it's on the incarnation.
See, Nathan Asius at one point says,
and I might be slightly paraphrasing here, but he says,
unless one has a pure mind and is trying to imitate the lives of the saints,
he can't ever understand their teachings.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
And also, you know, true love casts out fear.
Hmm.
So cast out your love God enough you won't be afraid of him anymore.
Yeah, it's cast out that impurity, that uncleanness, the abomination.
Right.
That love purifies.
Yeah.
Cool.
Right.
The love of God purifies.
But so this is that pollution, that impurity, right, idea is closely related to.
I think we may have even briefly talked about the word back when in the blessings and curses
episodes when we were talking about curse, that purification that is forgiveness is the removal
of that curse state and of the stuff, the kind of residue of sin that kind of brings it
about.
And this is transformational, in the same way that sin corrupts.
forgiveness.
brings sort of new life and restoration, right, and a new way of life. And this is part
of why, and you see this especially in the Gospels, that healing and forgiveness are always
closely linked together, right as...
as being parallel with each other.
That healing and forgiveness work in the same way.
This is where you get St. John Chris Austin's favorite
famous saying that the church is not a courtroom.
It's a hospital.
Yeah.
And a place where you especially see that in these terms,
and to kind of wrap up what we've been talking about
in this first half,
in Matthew 816 and 7.
which is a short little bit that gets skipped over really fast because there's sort of a story before that in Matthew 8 and a story after that in Matthew 8
this is kind of a transitional two verses but it's actually very important in terms of the topic we're addressing.
Yeah, and I think another reason this gets skipped over probably is it's like, oh yeah Jesus did some more good.
He's doing good all the time. Here's some more good. He's doing, you know, yeah.
Matthew chapter 8 verses 16 and 17. That evening...
They brought to him many who were oppressed by demons, and he cast out the spirits with a word,
and healed all who were sick. This was to fulfill what was spoken by the prophet Isaiah.
He took our illnesses and bore our diseases.
So, um, notice there, right? So Jesus is doing all of these healings,
right and then there's this quote from Isaiah
real easy to read over that. But if you go and look where that quotation for
Isaiah is from, it's from Isaiah 53. Okay. It's the suffering servant passage. Yeah,
right. Right. And so some of the folks we were addressing at the beginning of
this half, right? Isaiah 53 is a go-to, right? Christ says...
as born-ar iniquities, right?
By his stripes we're healed, right?
Talking about, you know, see, look, this is saying,
he's being punished for our sins, right?
But that's not how Matthew 8 reads it.
St. Matthew reads this totally differently, right?
St. Matthew reads this as, right,
this scripture being fulfilled,
he took our illnesses and borrower diseases,
took them, bore them.
is.
Obviously, doesn't mean that when Christ healed someone who was paralyzed, he became paralyzed.
Right. He's sort of absorbed there. Right. Yeah. Or that he healed the leper and he got leprosy.
Right. Like he took the leprosy for them. Right. It's clearly not what it means. Yeah.
Right. Means he took them away. He bore them away. They're gone. Right. And so here it's so
So since it Isaiah
Right. The healing language and the forgiveness of sins language is all mixed together. Why on what basis would you disagree with St. Matthew and say no forgiveness of sins works entirely differently.
than the healing of diseases.
Right.
Yeah, I mean, with those same Matthew and Isaiah are both paralleling those.
And how many times do we see?
the gospels, Jesus saying, your sins are forgiven you and he's healing them of a disease.
Well, he does that.
Yes.
Right.
Which is easier to say your sins are forgiven or to say rise up and walk.
Yeah.
Right.
He just forgives people their sins.
You're admitting that?
He's God.
He could do that.
he's not bound by any kind of necessity.
Right, and you notice the objection of the rulers of the synagogue is not
You know, wait a minute. All sin must be punished or God is adjust the objection of the synagogue rulers at that point is
Who is he thinking he could forgive sins only God can do that yeah, right?
You know leading us to all it's
Ask that Chris law to regret it God can do that right yeah wait. He's God. Oh, that's that's right
Yeah, right
So yeah
Yeah, and so partially here to wrap up the first half, just to bring back to mind some of the things that we're not going to laboriously go through it all again.
A lot of the things we've talked about in terms of sin on the show that are then connected to this idea of forgiveness.
as we've already mentioned at least.
So, the idea of sin in the singular that St. Paul uses
that goes all the way back to Cain,
right? Sin is crouching at your door.
It wants to master you, you.
Master of demonic force of sin. Right. And as St. Paul later says, you know, all things are permissible to me, but I will not be mastered by anything. Right.
That that sin is this power in the world.
Sins are passions because they make us passive. And when we yield to them and allow them to take control of us, that is transformative to us in the direction of the demonic.
Yeah, alright.
And we give...
the demonic of place in our lives.
Therefore, on the flip side,
this is why we're at least summarily bringing it up
again here.
On the flip side, that means that forgiveness represents
being set free from that, being healed from that.
You know, saved from regaining freedom to allow
for self mastery and self control in the future.
Yeah, saved from and saved for both at the same time.
Yep, yep.
Alright, we're going to take a short break and
and we'll be back with the second half of the Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the second half
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
If you enjoy listening to Agent Faith Ray,
podcasts.
Consider making them accessible to the members of our community who are hearing impaired
by commissioning the transcription of a podcast episode.
For only 75 cents per audio minute, most podcasts can be transcribed, and thereby it may
be accessible to those who cannot hear the podcasts.
Visit ancientface.com slash transcripts to learn how you can sponsor a transcript
and enable our brothers and sisters who are hearing impaired to...
Read podcast transcriptions.
Begin that ancientface.com slash transcripts.
Thank you.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
with Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
I'm going to get you a new one.
Thank you for that voice of Steve. This is the second half of the Lord of
Spirits, our episode on confession, where not taking calls, unless somehow you know
that we're recording right now. But wait for you. Okay, you didn't call. This is a
pre-recorded show. Father Stephen and I both thought in Texas on undisclosed
official business. But welcome back. So we just talked to not involved
smuggling barbecue sauce across the board.
No, because I mean, I spend a significant amount of my life in North Carolina and there's
not such a thing as barbecue sauce.
At least an Easter Carolina barbecue.
There is in Texas.
I know, I know.
And honestly, I've said this many times, but it's true.
I have room in my stomach for all of God's barbecues, but there is a hierarchy.
There is a hierarchy.
Yeah, I should say the the greatest culinary achievement of my time in Texas
was when I was at the prison and I'll just leave it at that
with people who don't know speculate. Folks used to with their making a big pot of
chili, spray pepper spray into it. I have dead serious.
Ah
Wow, that's kind of horrifying.
Pepper spray is just concentrated capsicum.
Is it, I hope so?
It's in hot sauce, it's just super concentrated.
It's still, I mean, see,
you hit a big pot with just a little, you know,
stirred up.
Good chili.
Rock your socks.
It's not food grade.
Wow, I'm glad you were-
the confess that sin right here on the surface of Lord's presence. I don't know that that was a sin.
Texans don't think it was. Wow. That and having jalapenos in cornbread. That was a degedious
plan somebody came up with. Well yeah. I mean, that's yeah. Yeah. I'm on board with that.
Okay, so in our first half we basically established and talked about that God can and
indeed and does forgive sins.
And we kind of started moving a little bit towards how that works.
And now in this half, we're going to talk about how God forgives sins.
So let's start with the Old Testament, right?
That's always a good place to start.
Yeah.
Eventually this evening, we will actually get to confession.
Right.
Promise.
As is our want that will be very late the episode.
I mean, you know, even though I...
episodes do tend to be of leisurely length.
You know, the truth is that almost all of the Christian practices that we talk about
are built on thousands of years. Thousands of years. Right?
So really, our episodes are very short. Lightening fast, little quick summaries.
Yes. Yeah. And the great cosmic scheme of things.
The eye blink.
Exactly.
So.
And this is another one we're not going to super belabor, but we're going to hopefully
remind folks about mostly.
And that is that through obviously in the Old Testament at least, once you get to the
patriarchal period, so for at least for the vast majority of the Old Testament, and I would
say pretty much the whole thing.
forgiveness primarily comes through sacrificial ritual. That is the primary sort of way that God works forgiveness in people's lives.
And so the part that we're going to kind of review and not
belabor because we did three episodes on this is that
sacrifices come in the context of hospitality.
hospitality, sort of central form.
The main form of hospitality is the sharing of a meal.
Right?
And so, sacrifices are such meals.
And those meals are celebrations and actualizations of restored or deepened communion and relationship.
Yep. Right, between peoples.
So, right, if I invite you over to sit down for a meal, it might be we're reconciling.
might just be where...
already good friends and we're going to become closer friends by sharing some more time together.
The important part for us here tonight, with our topic tonight,
to reiterate is that the meal part of the sacrifice, that's after the fact of forgiveness.
Yeah, it's it's not that if you give God this you know if you say okay
God we're gonna have a meal. I hope you're gonna come and forgive me. That's not what's going on.
Right. And it's also not there's a difference between a ritual sacrifice and ritual magic.
Right. Because ritual magic is, you know, if I do this, then I will get this result. You know,
if I do this, then God must respond in the following way. Right. Right. And even among pagans, by the way,
there was a distinction between ritual sacrifice and ritual magic.
And then...
The pagans understood that with a regular sacrifice, the God could tell you to buzz off, whatever
they were sacrificing to, could still had free agency.
Whereas with magic they did.
But God had to reiterate this, and he reiterates it over and over again in the Hebrew Bible
and the Old Testament, that this doesn't work by magic.
that if the sacrifice isn't following on repentance, then it doesn't do any.
Yeah, I mean there's a lot. I'll say there's all this places where God says your sacrifices are not acceptable to me
And it's because you're unrepentant
Right, right. He literally gets to the point where he says to the prophets just stop. Yeah
Stop offering sacrifices, right because this whole I'm gonna live however I want to live and then
You know go and offer sacrifices so that I'm good
I give the clear.
So to that.
I'm like, mobster religion, I think.
You know, like, you know, wear a guild.
It's wear guild.
Yeah, you're going out, you're, you know, you're,
you're going out as a mobster and you're, you know,
having people whacked and, and, you know,
engaging in all kinds of graft and corruption and everything.
But then, you know, you go to church on Sunday.
And, wait, pay off the right government officials.
Yeah, you know, and, and, and it's sort of, okay,
right? That dog don't hunt.
Right. Right. So, and a place where you really see this after the fact nature is when
Christ says, you know, if you're bringing your gift to the altar and you realize that
someone has something against you, leave it, go be reconciled with your brother, and then
come back and then come and make your offer. Yeah, I mean, and this makes sense just on
a kind of a human real, a human relational level too, right? Like, if you are going to share
a meal with somebody.
that you are in an antagonism with,
you need to make that antagonism right
before the other person's even gonna be willing
to go to lunch with you.
You know?
Yeah, yeah.
So this is an after,
and by the way,
Christ's talking about bringing gifts to an altar,
kind of applies that someone reads
that text would have an alter they were bringing gifts to.
But anyway, sacrifices in the New Testament.
How about that?
Right, but so it's afterward.
Right.
And so in the case of the, within the Torah,
within the functioning of the Torah,
the fact of after the fact,
right of what you were doing was
generally restitution. Most since involved some kind of restitution. I killed
your goat, I'm going to give you a goat. I did this amount of damage to you, I
I give you the money.
I stole from you, I give it back plus four times more.
So there's this restitution that's made, and then after the restitution is made, then
the meal, then the sacrifice, then the ritual that sort of seals it.
But this means that sin is being treated not as an individual personal private matter.
The problem is not between you...
and God only, right? And I know there's someone out there. As soon as I said that,
they're already typing a social media post somewhere to say, well, wait a minute,
in Psalm 51 or 50 of the Greek, David says against you and you only have I sinned.
Right? There's somebody doing that right now. Stop typing. Think for a second.
again is a
literal interpretation of that true.
Yeah, I mean there are other hurt parties involved.
He didn't sit against Firaia?
Right.
If he didn't sit against Bashima?
Yeah.
He's not denying that.
It is great solve of repentance.
David is not denying that he hurt anyone else.
Yeah, it's a kind of emphatic.
I mean only gets used in the scriptures.
Yes, the scripture is kind of emphatic.
Yes, yes.
This is a poetic right.
description. So stop type. Don't add us, bro. Yeah. The point is, right. And that's
true because sin always involves hurting others. Yeah. Right. Even if you sin completely by yourself,
right, you hurt others in ways that you may not immediately realize. Okay. If you are a
Merry Pursuitory.
person in a relationship just to give an example and you secretly watch pornography.
Your spouse or the other person may never find out about it.
They never know, right?
But the damage that has done to you will affect your relationship with that other person.
Yep.
Because it changes. And therefore it will affect them. Yeah, it changes who you are. Yes. Yeah. So there are always consequences and ripple effects. No man is an island.
Right.
And so there's always restitution in the sense of repair and healing that has to happen
beyond just you yourself in order to make things right.
No.
And repairing that damage within yourself and with other people, right, is what needs
to happen for the forgiveness to happen that's going to be celebrated in the sacrifice.
Another example, and I know I overuse this example, right, but is if, again, if you're a married
person and you go and commit adultery, you cheat on your spouse, right?
You can't just say, come home and say.
say, well, you know what? I've metania, right? The word for a
pen is a great means to think again. And I've rethought honey.
And what I did was wrong. And I will never do it again. So just go
ahead and forgive me.
Yeah, try that. No, don't try that. Don't try that. That's not
going to work. And neither is by the way, well, I could
fest to God that I committed adultery. And he's forgiven me. So
now you forgive me too, honey, right? Yeah. That's not going to
Well, or you know as as
Elysees Everett McGill
Says in Obrother were art thou you know it might put you square with the Lord, but the state of Mississippi can be a little more hard-nosed
so
Right so this is this is a reality right of rest of your repairing the damage done
Right and we see a positive example of this really clearly in the story of the keys
Yes.
So Zacchaeus is a tax collector, right?
Nobody likes the IRS, but tax collectors were way worse, right?
So he's a Roman collaborator, signing with them against his own people, helping them
oppress him.
He's extorting money from people, robbing them quite literally, right?
That's how he makes a living, a very good one, right?
So Christ goes to eat with him.
And Christ is going to end up saying to today salvation has come to this household, right?
But he doesn't do that when he walks in the door.
He could have, right, because he's Christ, right?
He is salvation, right?
He could have said that when he walked in the door of Zacchaeus' house.
But he doesn't.
And this story shows us something for that reason, right?
He says that after Zacchaeus has stood up publicly in front of the other people there, in
in front of the community.
who he's been sinning against.
He says, half of what I have I'm going to give to the poor and everything I stole I'm
going to pay back five times.
And it's after he says that publicly to the community that Christ says today salvation
has come to this house, because this too is a child of Abraham.
Because the change has been made.
Right.
Now he is a child of Abraham.
Now, so...
has come, right? Because of that restitution. And then another sort of note in
terms of how this works in sacrificial offerings is because we made the point
that forgiveness is about purification, right? And you can see this element of
purification distinguishable from the element of the sacrificial meal in that
that purification takes place through what you might call the by-products of a sacrificial
offering.
Okay.
So sort of given off.
Right.
Exuded.
So if you're offering incense, right, that smoke.
Smoke.
Yeah.
Right.
It's the smoke that has this purificatory quality, as we've talked about before on the
show.
with an animal sacrifice, it's blood.
Right, it's the blood of the animal,
which expressly is not eaten.
Right, right, it's separated from the meal, right,
but that blood has that purificatory quality,
i.e., on the day of atonement.
And the fact that that particular animal
or that particular incense has been offered
Sacrificially.
is what makes that byproduct the blood of the smoke
sacred and gives holy and gives it this purificatory
effect. Yeah, it's not that the...
I did the offering. It's not that the thing
itself, like that that blood is purifying or that smoke is purifying,
it's that in the context of it being offered as a sacrifice, it has that effect.
It's not a medicine, so to speak, in the sense of like just swallow it.
and for it all be good.
Like it's within the relationship with God.
Right, right.
And this is touching upon some of the things
we said in our episode on the Eucharist, right?
This is why we have body and blood, right?
Body participating in the sacrifice, blood purification,
right, of the person from sin.
So, now we're going to
talk to the rock. So, Duane Johnson, if you're listening, please call in. Yes.
Rock the Duane Johnson, if you feel, you know, switching and raising of the eyebrow.
I don't remember if we've ever talked about him on this show before, but I do have to point out, you know,
a little sort of local pride is that he went to high school in nearby Bethlehem, Pennsylvania. So,
We claim him as a lehi val liite. I don't know that that's the right word. I don't know.
Well in town was a wrestling hub back in the day.
Yeah, that's amazing.
The territory system.
It's amazing.
Yep, yep.
So Dwayne, Colin, all right.
Well, we just edited out the 20 minutes
that we waited for him to call.
He'd ever called, so.
Shockingly.
I know.
I thought his rock sense would tingle.
Disappointingly.
Hybrow would rise.
Yeah.
And he would pick up a phone and call us.
No.
Yeah.
So we're going to have to talk about some other black Adam.
I mean, come on, man.
Anyway, not the actual rock we were talking about.
Go figure.
So we are talking about Moses and the rock, okay, which may or may not have been one
rock, but we won't go down that rabbit trail now.
And may or may not have been the name of your first band.
There are two instances. Everybody wants a rock to tie a piece of.
Hey, there we go.
So, and, and, I am largely cribbing this understanding of these stories from a now-departing
man who is probably
What are the people most responsible for me being here talking to today?
Say wait, William Shadner isn't dead is he but whom I will not identify he is not he is 91 years
Yeah, let's say it's not William Shadner. All right
So no, this is more directly responsible than that
but so
There is this first episode where Moses is going to bring water from the rock
Okay, right.
And so the details of this sometimes get lost in the telling of the story, sort of the Sunday
school version.
I'm not going to ruin the Sunday school version of it, but I'm just going to add to it
and nuance it a little bit.
So I'm being nicer today.
But so people remember, they don't have water, right?
they're in the desert, they're in the wilderness.
The people start grumbling again.
And in their grumbling, they decide what they really ought to do is kill Moses and go back
to Egypt because they had it better there.
And so in the midst of that, right, Moses and God are speaking to each other.
And God says that the way he's going to handle this and what happens
is that we're told that Yahweh comes and stands on the rock. So this is another one of those
episodes where God apparently has a body and stands somewhere, see previous episodes.
And then Moses is told to strike the rock with his rod.
This rod, as we've talked about, is recently his last episode, was the symbol of authority
and of judgment.
So the idea here in this image is that is an image of God voluntarily taking upon himself
hatred, the judgment, the...
slander directed against him by the people and in return giving them water to drink, giving them life in return.
And this is taken to be in the New Testament. St. Paul being the most obvious place where he says,
the rock was Christ. You can't get more obvious than that. To be Christ, right?
Not just an image of Christ, but first of all,
that that was Christ who was standing on the rock.
Yeah.
But that this image of Christ,
taking upon himself the scorn, the hatred,
right, the judgment of the people, right?
And one of the things that often gets left out is,
there's so much, and I understand why there is
because
of the way in which texts have been weaponized against people, especially in Western Europe,
but not only in Western Europe over the centuries. But over whose responsible for Christ's death,
right, that we kind of lose out on the fact that the whole point of having both the Jewish leaders
and pilot there emphasized in the Gospels is that the Jews and the Gentiles, that it's everybody.
Right, in agreement, right, but Christ takes all of that upon himself and gives life in return.
Right. But then there's this second episode at the other end of the wilderness journey.
And we won't go down this rabbit hole, but St. Paul refers to it.
in the passage we just quoted in First Corinthians.
He says that not only was the rock Christ,
but the rock followed them in the wilderness.
So it's the same rock for St. Paul.
And for a lot of other Jewish writers in that period,
but there's a second episode with the rock
and high pita ends if you're listening.
There's this second episode with the rock.
And in this case, when the people are grumbling again,
God tells Moses to go and speak.
speak to the rock. Yeah, but he gets mad and he hits it instead. Right, he's mad at the people,
he's kind of mad at God, and he strikes the rock again with his rod, meaning he and his anger
joins the people in sort of casting this judgment at God. Right. And that's why this is such a serious
sin on Moses' part that it would be.
that he would not be able to enter the Promised Land because of it. That he would not get to because of it.
Right. It wasn't just, I gave you instructions and you didn't follow the instruction, right?
Right.
This is why it's treated so seriously.
And the idea there, if we understand again the rock to be Christ, is that Christ suffered and died once.
Now he offers forgiveness.
when we speak to him. And that, you know, this is part of that understanding that really gets
fleshed out, for example, in Hebrews. This shift from repeated sacrifice to participation in
the one sacrifice of Christ and Christ, that his intercessions as high priest, right, that
This is one little
piece in the background of that. So, but it's important to know, as we get ready, to move
into the third half, where we will finally actually talk about confession, right, that
making restitution entailed confession. Right, right. So, it's not laid out like this
This person must go and admit...
what they did and then make restitution. It just talks about making restitution. But the confession
part is implied, right? Like someone has robbed you, I show up at your house to give you five times
what was stolen. You're going to kind of figure out on the guy who took it, right? You're sort of
admitting it by making restitution, right? Like you can't really have one without the other, right?
Right.
And so...
So the reason we want to reiterate that here is that confession that we're now going
to move into talking about also entails restitution.
Yeah, you have to make things right.
Right.
That again, like in that adultery example, just admitting what you did all by itself, right,
does not fix the situation.
two things always go together.
Right. But what doesn't have to be there, right, is more suffering.
Now, sin causes suffering.
When you sin against someone, you probably are causing them to suffer.
The consequences of that may cause you to suffer. But inflection of suffering
does not have more suffering beyond that does not make it better.
Yeah, I mean, and there's.
point in any of the commandments in the Old Testament, for instance, or anywhere in the New
Testament, where it says, you know, and correct me if I'm wrong with this, because I'm not
super certain about what I'm about to say. But I mean, there's no point where it says,
you know, and let him be flagged or let him be tortured, you know, there are things that
require someone to be removed from the community. Right. Whether there's a practice that
Develops.
lashes being given at Citigogs, right? But that's not prescribed in the Torah. God doesn't say to do that.
Right. But yeah, and but in part this is getting back to where we were at the beginning of
of the first half in that, right, there's no punishment, right, required.
right and that punishment at any rate would not involve like the inflicting of
suffering. Right and so you never see animals that are going to be sacrificed
being tortured, being treated cruelly. That in itself would be a sin. Yeah right and
so like the restitution we're talking about is not whipping yourself, right?
Self-laculation.
Right, it's not degrading yourself, right? It's not inflicting harm on yourself, right?
It is about fixing the harm you've already done
Through through sin. That's what restitution is, right?
And so
brief note to my fellow priests
We're going to talk more now as part of our segue.
We're going to talk in the...
third half about confession as it's practiced in the Orthodox Church now, well from the New Testament
until now. But my fellow priests, don't make things into punishments through confession.
Right, here's what I mean by that.
Sometimes, and this isn't always the pre-sintent.
But sometimes people will read whatever they're told to do after confessing it's in as
being a punishment anyway.
Yeah, because, I mean, this is just the way that our culture tends to think.
Right.
And so if you go and sorry to our Roman
Catholic friends because I know this is super common.
But if you for example say, well, go say so many prayers.
Right?
Because you did thing X.
Well, number one, you've made prayer a punishment.
I don't know, that's the message we want to send.
Right?
Yeah.
And once they've said that many prayers is like,
well, you good.
Now I'm done with that whole praying thing.
What I have to do that again until I screw up.
Right?
That's not good, right?
Or from my perspective, those may just be my personal subregative, even worse, go and
read so much of the Bible every day for a certain period of time because you did this thing.
And it's like, oh great, making the Bible a punishment.
That's right.
Yeah, I mean, there's, yeah, or like, occasionally my kids will say something like, do I have
to go to
church, you know, particularly like if they've just lost their minds, you know, and my wife
will sometimes say, you know, bring them to vespers, or whatever. And they'll like, you
know, I'm being punished by being sent to vespers, like, no, that's not, you're not being
punished. Like I go to vespers and no one's punishing me, you know, I love it. But it's really
like, look, no, you get to do this. And that's not ironic. That's not ironic. It's, it's
This is...
how we're supposed to be living.
So let's move to do.
This is gonna help you.
Yeah, let's move into where we're supposed to be.
Do better.
Right.
Yeah, exactly.
So just a brotherly admonition.
I think,
That's who everyone else don't take things as punishment.
Yeah, yeah, right.
And I think mainly the main thing,
I mean, you and I are both confessors.
Yeah, I think the main thing especially is to,
I try to communicate to people like,
Look, this is, this is...
to help. This is not to punish. This is not because you did something wrong and I had to do this
own risk thing. Like, no, this is this is, if it's too much, if it's too much of that person,
then the question might be like, well, okay, what's, what is going to bring them into the good habits,
you know? So, so yeah, it's, it's supposed to be healing and beneficial just like taking even,
even taking medicine is not a punishment. It's, it's for health. So yeah. All right, we're going to
take another stroke.
break and we'll be right back with a third half of the Lord of Spirits. Father
Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take
your calls on the second half of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hi, this is Father Evan Arvatoz.
Jesus has...
words to disciples will go and make disciples of all the nations. Unfortunately, many
parishes are struggling to follow this commandment. In my new book, Reclaiming the Great Commission,
I offer a roadmap to help us get back on track. Drawing from my 20 years of parish experience,
holy scripture, and insights from research and visits for churches across the United States,
I discuss how you and your community can implement changes that will transform,
revitalize when we need your parish.
Learn how to diagnose, remove the barriers you face, deal with resistance to change,
define what a healthy parish looks like, lead with purpose, and create a parish health
plan.
Written for clergy, council members, ministry leaders, small groups, and all committed
parishioners, this book will help any church in its journey to reclaim the Great Commission.
Reclaiming the Great Commission is now available on paperback ebook and audio book at store.angianfay.com
that store.AncientFaith.com
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Welcome back everyone, it's the third half of the Lord of Spirits and
This is a pre-recorded episode, so we're not taking any calls this time around.
And we're talking about confession.
So we just...
You know, some people complain that the show has three halves.
I know.
And I must point out, as Aristotle said, everything that comes in threes is perfect.
I mean, it's...
We could call them.
three thirds but no I don't know I don't know it just wouldn't be as a half is
more than a third that's right exactly and I really feel like people are
getting a show and a half at least and there was that one episode we did that
had four halves that was a double show so that is true that didn't happen once
yeah yeah yeah that's because we're orthodox so for every rule there's an
exception. Right? Exactly. There's a Sunday of the cross, if you will.
Yeah. There was a there were like five liturgy nerds who just got really excited about that
roughly. Wait, wait, I'm working this out. I'm working it out. Yeah. We know who you are.
We're happy for you. Yes. So all right. So in the first half we talked about the fact that
God can and does indeed do does forgive and then second has the forgiveness he does
He does a forgiveness. He did a forgiveness.
And the second half we talked about how that is enacted, especially in the Old Testament,
but of course, edging on into the New Testament.
But now we're going to go fully into the New Testament and speak about the way that forgiveness
is given by God, starting then and continuing on now in the Orthodox Church even here in
in 2023.
So yeah, yeah.
And not only how...
but through whom? Through whom? Yes. This is where it gets uncomfortable for some people.
Yeah. Yeah. And part of the answer is through you.
Wow, you almost spoke with Wynian. Oh really? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. You don't have to speak in tongues. You don't have to speak in tongues.
You don't have to speak in tongues. It's a plural. Second person plural.
So, I could have been speaking Pennsylvania and gone for-
youngs. Well, that's Western Pennsylvania. Youngs,
yens. Yeah. They don't count. I mean, it's the other
Pennsylvania. What can I say? Is there like an East Coast West
Coast rap beef within the state of Pennsylvania? Yeah,
pretty much. Like out here, you will hear some people, not
everybody, but yours some people actually say use. They
that's the plural out here is use. Ks. You hear use guys,
but use that's more Jersey. That's Jersey bleed. Right, I
I mean I'm only 20
25 miles from New Jersey.
But yeah, I mean, you would think also that there would be like a divide with the
Eagles on this end and the Steelers on the other end, but it actually is not so much East
West.
The Steelers seem to have actually most of the state and then sort of the South East as
the Eagles, roughly, but I think the line runs to the Lehigh Valley.
So I don't know.
But yes, that's good.
A lot of that is, I think, related to the win-loss records of the 15th.
probably true to be fair.
Sort of like the bets of the Yankees.
Right.
It's true.
You know, it's true.
Yes.
Well, as far as your East-West view goes, hit them up.
So confession in the New Testament.
Right.
And so the first place, as you read through the New Testament,
that you get to, one of the most important plays
where this is talked about is in Matthew chapter 18.
and
This is the part that we're going to talk about is within a passage that's well known in a lot of circles.
In that it's the passage that sort of talks about what gets called church discipline.
Right? That if there's someone who's sitting in the church, right, this is the part that is more well known.
that you should
first go to them individually, privately, then bring someone else to them and then if you
still can't work it out, that you bring it before the whole church, right?
Yeah.
That part people are very familiar with.
But in the midst of that, there's a statement that kind of gets glossed over but that is
probably the most important part of it.
Yeah.
So, verse 18.
And I'm going to go ahead and use Southern American plural rather than throw myself into
epic Pennsylvania feud of the second person plural. Truly, I say to y'all, whatever y'all
bind on earth, shall be bound in heaven and whatever y'all loose on earth, shall be
loosed in heaven. Yes, you used y'all there to point out that the
you is plural. plural, that's right. As opposed to all y'all, which is what I like to
call the pervasive plural, meaning every single last one of you. Yes, all y'all.
Yeah.
So.
So the idea here is that, and this is within that,
what, whatever you as a group, the community, the church,
the ecclesia, the assembly, whatever you all,
bind on earth, will be bound in heaven, whatever you loose on earth,
shall be loose in heaven.
So this means that, right, there is...
obviously implied here that there is an agreement, right, that there's a mutual agreement that is taking place
and that this has the effect of the forgiveness or not of sin.
Yeah, and I mean this is the reason why I think this is uncomfortable for some Christians is that
that as Christ says here, whatever you and he's talking to the
Apostles, whatever you bind on earth is going to be bound in heaven, whatever you lose on earth will be
loosed in heaven. In other words, their action has a corresponding action in the kingdom of God, right?
And that they're connected and they're not separable. And I think the problem that some people would have with
this is like, well, my forgiveness is not in the hands of some person, you know, not some
in person whatever but I mean you can't get around it. Jesus is actually saying this.
And the way that some people try to get around it is they say well you know that was for
the apostles and then kind of not after that. But then that sets up another sort of question
like well why would Jesus give that to just them? And then it just stops when their last one dies.
I don't know. Yeah. And why would why would Saint Matthew bother recording it then?
Yeah.
right knowing it was good to meet anything to later generations at all right but also you have
the basic problem of the context is this talking about in the context of the church right you're
bringing this issue with this brother or sister at Christ before the whole church
And in fact our
German friends use the fact that this passage is talking about the church to say that Jesus couldn't have possibly said it because it's about the church
Right because their theology means that there's not a church at this point and so therefore he couldn't be talking about the church
But so it seems very clear to pretty much all readers who aren't trying to get around it
That this is talking about how things are going to be done in the church
Yeah, right now it's ridiculous that Jesus didn't say it because you know
So.
These are folks who want to say that Jesus is just a human and know the future
Right.
Possibly have predicted that there would be a church.
Yeah, I mean there's yeah, yeah, yeah
And they're also ignoring the fact that Ecclesi was used for the assembly of the Old Testament
Yeah, right.
He's simply Israel.
There is this Greek translation of the Old Testament that uses the word yeah
So you know, our 90th century children friends are wrong as usual but
The point just being this is very clearly the text associated with the church
Right.
Right? And so what this means is that is not that, right?
Independent from God.
Some kind of church authority, which isn't what's being talked about here,
it's talking about the church as a whole, or even the churches of a whole
controls your eternal destiny. Right? That's not what it's talking about.
That's taking it in the wrong direction. What it's saying is that
As we were talking about last time in the episode about org.
Nation God works through people in the world. Yeah, right. And God forgives people. It's God who's doing the forgiving. Right.
But he forgives people through the community of the church.
That is where that forgiveness is received and experienced is within the community.
Yep, can't get away from that communal aspect as a whole. It's not just me and Jesus. Right as opposed
to me off by myself.
And whatever sins I may or may not have committed
is nobody's business at the church.
In fact, every time I go to the church
I'm gonna dress as nicely as possible
and pretend as hard as I can
that I'm completely seamless, right?
Because otherwise they'll all judge me.
We'll get back to that later.
But so it's in this communal context, right?
And so because forgiveness comes in that communal.
context of the community, confession takes place in that same community context. And so Martin Luther's
favorite book of the Bible, Epistle St. James, talks about this. Yeah, St. James writes this, therefore,
confess your sins to one another.
And pray for one...
another that you may be healed. The prayer of a righteous person has great power as it is working.
Again, that's the ESV. So you might be used to the prayer of a righteous man availeth much,
which is the way it is in my head. Or is powerful and effective? Yes, right, right. I think that's the
maybe, maybe, never inspired by it.
Yeah.
Right.
But so notice, it's confess your sins to one-
another and pray for one another that's given as a command. Why do you do that? So that in order that
you may be healed. Yeah, it's conditional. Yes. That is the means by which you will experience healing
from your sins. Notice again, healing is what's being used. Not juridical terminology.
Dealing is used, but the way that happens is through...
messengers to one another within the Christian community.
Yeah. Right.
And another example, there are a lot more, but another example that's good in
Acts 19, verse 18.
Yeah.
Also, many of those who are now believers came confessing and divulging their
practices.
So all their full way of putting it.
Yes.
So in case there's any ambiguity about what confessing means,
divulging their practices, right?
Divalging, like secrets.
Like, this is the stuff I've been doing secretly.
They're now making public and confessing.
And the reality is we're not running through every single
passage.
Right?
Yeah.
I was if you want to.
I was going to just add by the way, if you read
couple verses after that. I can case you wonder what those practices there devolging are.
It talks about magic, magic and burning their magical books and all this kind of stuff.
Like it's their confessing the occult in this particular case.
They had some practices going on. Yeah.
But we can keep going on with these examples. But, and you could do this study yourself,
no one in the New Testament confesses their sins to God privately. There's not a single example.
Yeah, so if you're, if you believe in solar scriptura, and especially if you're the kind that says
that if it's not written in the scripture, you're not allowed to do it, then you have kind of an
issue there. Right. Because the, the New Testament pattern, the biblical pattern is public confession.
Right. Within the church community. Yeah. That's what we're to do. Yeah. And I mean, and, and,
and according to the Bible.
And the word itself, like the basics
sense of the word. And I'm not just talking about etymology here, but although it does kind
of work out that way. But the word itself means, you know, eczema leases is to proclaim something
out publicly. Yes. And if you do a, if you want to go the word study route and do it on that
word of the New Testament, you will notice something is that there's two ways that that word is used.
One of them is confessing sin. The other one is confessing Christ.
Yeah, yeah, and you're not supposed to.
We could fast with our mouth that Jesus is Lord.
Right.
You know, just say, well, I privately within my heart
confessed Christ.
Right.
If you confesses me before men, yeah.
Yeah.
So in every case where it's talking about in that usage
of confessing Christ, it always means publicly, vocally.
Yeah.
Right.
And so to say, oh.
And then as in the examples we gave, in a whole bunch of cases, it clearly means that
about confessing sins also publicly verbally.
But well, there's a few cases I can find here that are kind of ambiguous.
So I'm just going to assume in those handful of ambiguous cases that it means something
completely different than all the other usages that hear it means privately in my heart and
home by myself, that's not a very good argument.
and we should
say that there's, we're not saying you should not confess your sins to God in your private
prayers. We're not saying that. But that's secondary to this.
I might be kind of saying. Oh really? Oh, okay. Well, I don't know. I mean, there are some
of the prayers. I mean, you know, there are some of the prayers. Let me be an extremist.
Yeah. I'm going to be an extremist. You're such a rigorous person. Steve and I swear.
Yes. Oh no, I'm a radical.
Yeah, but but I think the main thing I
I mean, there are, you know, like, for instance, daily prayers include prayers, you know,
right, about confessing sins and so forth.
Right.
But that's secondary.
It's secondary.
Right.
And they're mostly asking for healing.
But, um, I, well, let me put it this way.
I don't know that that's actually confessing.
Hmm.
I don't think that that's the verb we should use for it.
Okay.
Because part of what's going on here is God already knows.
Yeah, of course.
You're not giving him new information.
And you already know, because you did it.
Yeah.
We don't excuse me, man.
I know what it was you.
I know what I did.
Shack you.
Anyway.
Uh.
So
Whereas the practice of publicly and verbally saying out loud what it is that we did is a
different thing and has a different function.
right then I who already know thinking I guess to God who already knows
Right?
That's not the same thing.
That's a different thing.
And that other thing may have value too, right?
So we won't get into that.
Sure.
That other thing has some value.
But that's not confession in the same sense.
Okay.
Verbalizing, right?
Putting it out there in some kind of public, at least with someone else there, right?
Is a different thing.
a different experience when you do it.
someone who's done both, right?
And it accomplishes different things.
So yeah, I wouldn't say that I'm not saying the other thing has no value.
I'm saying maybe the best thing to do is use a different verb for that.
Right. Talk about praying for forgiveness on one hand
and talking about confession on the other hand as a public act.
Right. Okay. So yeah, I mean we say it's public, but the way that we actually practice it these days is not someone standing up in front of everybody and saying, okay,
although that's how it was done in the early church, we must say. Right. And that's what the New Testament reflects is what was actually done for the first few centuries. Yeah. And and honestly, I mean, I think even now, even though this is not sort of the normal way that we do it, I'm not suggesting that parishes take up this practice.
But there are some kinds of sins that
Someone needs to stand up and say to everybody,
this is what I did.
Like there's some kind of...
Like the kids.
Yeah, right, right.
You know, that there's...
Just he had sinned against all those people.
Right.
And it's interesting, you know, like,
you know, at least in American society,
that's kind of the one thing
that public people almost never do.
You know, like they may say something like,
I apologize if anyone was hurt.
You know, that kind of nonsense.
Yeah.
apologizers but it's not exactly...
Right.
It wasn't exactly ring true.
But so let me be a radical again.
I think it would be great if we brought it back but I don't think we ever will.
No, I can't see that happening.
Right.
And one of the things that cemented to me that we never will is I actually did an experiment
once.
And so if you were one of the people who ended up being part of my experience, meaning
you live in Charleston, West Virginia. You're listening to this.
apologize. Kind of. I mean, I don't totally regret doing it, but I'm sorry that you were
part of the experiment, experiment, if you were. And you're listening to this. Wow, this
is the thing to be the part that's going to be excerpted and we'll get go viral. I'm
sure. There was a point when I was at the cathedral in Charleston where you talk about
I'm like, need to curse people, go to...
confession. So I just gave my confession in a homily to the congregation. Oh wow. I just did it.
And I felt a certain rush while doing it. But there was a lot of people looking at me awkwardly.
Yeah. I can imagine. I mean, I know many of those people and shifting in their pews.
Oh
Yes, I'll bet.
That's a church that has pews.
Yeah, and so...
I can't honestly say I totally regret doing it.
Yeah, I think you're gonna say,
I feel bad for the people who I did it to.
I thought you were gonna say you made other people do it.
So this is not cool.
No, no, no, no, no.
Yeah, so that happened once.
But, but
But the reason I think it would be wonderful if we got back to it
Is that one of the things I encounter in hearing people's confessions is that everyone who comes to me for confession
thinks they're the most like hideous, malotorous, pervert in the world. Yeah, yeah
Right, and just their wicked at evil and everyone else in the church is so holy and pure and wonderful
Yeah, and you know this like them and this kind of thing is just
It's exas-
by especially by the experience of social media that everyone has where it's like,
well, there's this, in many cases, a beautiful curated version of people
that they put out, you know, my Instagram life. And, you know, everyone
else's marriages, everyone else's child rearing, everyone else's careers, all this kind of,
I've had people even say to me, you know, wow, you live such an amazing, great life,
whatever I'm like well
You know, you can ask my wife about the reality of the way that I am.
You know, I mean, but that's the reality of the way that these things work is whether
it's social media or just behavior in public, you know, because we all behave publicly.
It's all curated on some level.
We're all, you know, holding back and putting out particular things.
Yeah.
And being well mannered at everything is not the problem.
It's not bad to be polite.
So I don't think we'll ever
Like I said, I don't think we'll ever bring that practice back.
But if all of us within the church community could be more open with each other,
about the realities of the things that we're struggling with,
so that we would all realize, hey, wait, there's a bunch of other people
here struggling with the same thing.
Right. We're doing this again.
Yeah. Yeah. I mean, in that one.
That would be a great benefit to all of us.
Like, you know, we like to make our Protestant friends feel
uncomfortable.
But I mean, one thing I will say, especially for certain sectors
of evangelical Protestantism that have, you know, small groups
who do this kind of thing with each other on some level.
I mean, not that it's always healthy, not that it's always
healthy, but there are.
I mean, I've been, you know, when I was evangelical now,
who, wow, this is almost three years ago now.
but I mean,
And when I was, I remember experiencing that where people would openly talk about their
struggles with each other, which can feel super cringe for a lot of people.
But and can be, you know, like it can be distorted and abused and all that kind of stuff.
It can be.
But.
Sometimes that's even curated.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
But, but, but when it's done with actual real trust and love and friendship, it actually
is pretty great.
It actually is pretty great.
Yeah.
Um...
But so, yeah, as you said, that's not the current practice.
There are all kinds of reasons for that.
Right.
Many of which are springing to people's minds if they're thinking about, would they ever do that?
Yeah.
So, but so right now, the way it's done in the Orthodox Church is that you confess at the
front of the church, but that only the priest is there present with you hearing it.
Right?
But the priest is there.
representing the whole community, representing the congregation.
Right.
And we talked, see our last episode about ordination.
And so that's what the priest is doing there.
And I try to emphasize to people you're not really confessing
to me as an individual person.
Yeah, and the way...
I mean, not always, but the way that the sort of architecture of confession often is set up is you have a person facing maybe an icon of Christ or facing a cross or facing a Gospel book and the priest is beside them.
Yes.
I mean, there are cases in which confession is face to face and whatever, and that's nothing wrong, right? It's not wrong.
But, you know, the architecture is often set up to kind of really reinforces idea that you're confessing your sins to Christ and the priest hears confessions.
herb, but here's confessions. And as there is a witness, is there representing the congregation.
And praying with them as the congregation, right. And then so within that context, in terms
of the modern orthodox practice, and why are we going into the modern orthodox practice
as much as we are. I think a lot of if not all non orthodox people.
So probably have a lot of assumptions about how confession works, the contemporary Orthodox
church that are based on partially on how it's done in Roman Catholicism.
Probably more on how it's done in movies and TV shows.
Yeah, that's what I was going to say.
Half of the confession is probably mostly based on what people see in movies and stuff.
Yeah.
Right.
even actually what happens in Roman Catholicism, but even if you are aware of...
how it actually functions in Roectodocytosis
a bit different in the orthodox church in different ways.
And so one of the things that functions very differently
than most people probably think in the orthodox church
is what gets called penance.
Even in the orthodox church it gets called penance.
I don't think we should probably
start to think of it.
Some people just like to throw out the Greek word epitemia
and because no one knows what that means.
So it doesn't have the freight.
The penance does.
Because as we were mentioning at the end of the second half
penance has this connotation of punishment or suffering or now something you have to do
right or you won't be forgiven and you'll go to hell or something.
And all those assumptions get shoved in there, right?
Whereas what actually happens in terms of worth...
That ox confession is that you and your spiritual father, who the person you're confessing
to, have a conversation, right, longer short, about what it is you're struggling with, right?
And form kind of a treatment plan to use the medical metaphor, right?
Or a game plan of how to be more successful in that struggle in the future and continue
to work on it and try and replace.
bad habits that are causing you to fall into sin with good habits that will help you.
And give guidance in terms of that restitution stuff we were talking about, right?
When people have been hurt, you know, what do you need to do to try and make this right?
So that's what quote-unquote penance is in terms of the Orthodox practice,
trying to get at that restitution piece. And sometimes that can be complicated.
But yeah, it real life situations
You could be a lot of different people involved in different ways.
And I mean, and a lot of the kind of conversation that happens within confession is about trying to help the other person think about their life in a different way so that they can interpret it in a way that's going to enable that repentance.
Yeah.
So we...
That's kind of talking about losing, right, and God forgiving sins.
But we gotta, we gotta go to the other side of that, the less, less nice parts to talk about.
And that is the binding on earth, and binding in heaven part, right?
This is, which basically is excommunication.
Yeah, and it's a response to not repenting, right?
Yeah, X-ray, a lack over-petens, a lack of willingness to...
make restitution and try to restore.
And a lot of people, especially if they don't have any concept of how things work in the
Orthodox Church, again, from movies and TV depictions of Roman Catholicism.
And your Puritan settlers.
You know, excommunication is often understood as we're throwing you out and we never want
to see you again.
And our door, we're going to bird you at the stake.
Yeah, right.
And literally.
neither and their, you know, excommunication in the Orthodox context can mean a couple of different
things and none of them is that. You know, so there's, yeah. There's excommunication and there's
excommunication. Yeah. So there's the sense of, okay, you're going to remain part of the church
community but you're going to refrain from communion for a while, you know. And it's for a while,
it's not permanent, it's for a while. Right. Because, again, leave your gift. Right. Right.
and joy be reconciled.
So...
the work of repentance and restoration has to happen before it's safe for you to
again. There has to be this purification on your way to have a meal with God.
And the other sense really, probably the better word is anathema, which sounds
even worse. But even so, like when Solomon
and the atlas are laid down.
by ecumenical councils, right,
or repeated in the Sonata Conoporthodoxy.
It's not...
If you have a curse, yeah.
It's not pure rejection.
It's not.
It's about, okay, this person's unrepentance is so great
that they have to put outside the church community
until they are repentant.
See, it's still got that until it's not,
we're sending you to hell.
Thank you.
we can't do that. You know so it's right. It says nothing to do with who goes to heaven who goes to hell. Right exactly.
And neither the alphabetized verse that we're hoping. Right yeah like when we when we get up
on the Sunday if you go to a church on the Sunday of Orthodoxy where they read the anathema as I should say.
When they say that the Aryans are a curse it right.
If you are an Aryan, right, there's a solution.
for that repent of Aryanism. Now you're not an Aryan anymore and you're not a curse it.
Right. And I mean most of those Nathamas are leveled against those who teach or those who say
XYZ. Yeah. So stop teaching that and stop saying it. Right. Exactly. Yeah. That's what it's
aimed at. Yeah. Try to get you to stop. Yeah. And also, I should also point out it's not to those
who think it's not leveled at opinions it's they're directed at those who are
actively doing something public. That's what's because this is okay. Yeah, I've probably done this
other show before, but this is one of my hobby horses. The word heresy, right? Does it mean to choose
stop with the anomologies? Okay, the word heresy was used in the Greek of the time to refer to a
to be a heretic means to be a sectarian.
Right.
It means to draw people off after yourself,
to make your own little following, right?
To develop a cult of personality around yourself.
That's why almost all heresies are named after a person.
Right?
And so you don't become a heretic by being wrong.
Aries was not a heretic because he was wrong.
Aries is a heretic because he would not repent.
Right.
accepted when his bishop told him he was wrong.
when other bishops told him he was wrong.
When all the bishops of the church got together and told him he was wrong,
he still refused to admit he was wrong.
And continued to teach the same things and tried to convince other people that he was right.
That's what makes you a heretic.
Yep.
Right.
Not just not not getting something right.
Right?
Because if that was the case, we'd be in a lot of trouble.
Yeah.
Right.
It's almost everybody if you ask them to explain the Trinity as a heretic.
Yeah.
Right.
Okay.
But most people are not going out and saying, no, my understanding of the Trinity is the correct
one and everyone who disagrees with me is a heretic.
And you need to come and join my church that I'm starting for the real Trinitarians.
That person is a heretic.
Right.
Axe ground.
It's a nice startbacks now.
Right.
So that's the...
So that's when we're anatomizing someone as a heretic. That's what we're talking about.
Right? Right. So this isn't about proclaiming hatred for particular people or groups of people.
It's the exact opposite. It's because we love them that we're calling on them to repent
of their false beliefs and practices. Right?
But the reason for why is this the sort of
removal from the community for lack of repentance, right? Why is this a thing? Right? Well, it's
because sin is still a communal issue. Yep. Just like it was in the old covenant. You're hurting
other people when you sin. We as we said earlier. And the there are examples of this in the New
You Testament, right?
First Corinthians 5, maybe one of the most infamous ones, right?
where St. Paul asked to write to the church in Corinth because there's a guy who's sleeping
with it's not clear, totally clear in the text whether this is his mother, his stepmother,
his mother-in-law.
It's bad.
Either way, it's gross.
It's incest.
It incest.
Yes, it incest under Louis Vuitton's 18 in any case, right?
But, see Paul's writing to the whole church about it, not just sending him a letter.
And he's writing to the whole church about it because the whole church knows about it and isn't doing anything.
Right. Right. Is just sort of letting it happen.
And he implies in the text that they kind of think they're being open-minded and good at understanding by not doing anything about it.
Like they think positively of themselves for not doing anything about it.
Oh, how non-judgmental we are.
rather than addressing it, right?
And why does St. Paul wanted to address,
because he hates that guy?
Well, no, because that guy will never repent
if someone doesn't confront him, clearly.
Right?
So it's about the salvation of that man's soul.
Jude, one verse 12 talks about a certain group of people
within that community.
who he calls sort of a stain on their love fees, right?
When they get together to celebrate the Eucharist, having these people there,
it's sort of tainting the whole thing, right? Sort of wrecking the whole thing.
And what Saint Paul prescribes in 1 Corinthians 5, and he makes references again in 1 Timothy 1 verse 20,
is that that person be handed over to Satan. That sounds really crazy, right? Like, that sounds like
like he's saying, you know.
send him to hell, right, right, given the devil, right. But keep reading, right. He's handed over to
Satan for the destruction of the flesh and the salvation of his soul. He's being put out of the
community back into the world, right. It's under the influence of the power of the evil one, right.
But as we've talked about many times on this show, what are the demons out there for?
Why does-
God let them stay out there to afflict the wicked and drive them to repentance.
So, the idea here is that this person is being put out there into the world that's under
the curse, anathema, so that this ultimate step may finally, you know, to use terminology,
We hit them out the hit rock bottom, bring them to repentance finally.
And Paul is also picking up here on a Jewish understanding.
It's kind of an inverted kind of martyrdom,
where the person's death itself,
and everything related to it,
in a way may offer...
some kind of atonement for their sin.
Yeah.
And like I said, it's hard to totally explain, right?
Other than that, obviously they're gonna be
enduring hardship and that kind of thing, right?
And so there's a certain kind of,
it's kind of a weird inverted eschis or something.
That's part of what,
See Paul is getting out with the death of the flesh of the
of the body there. But the core thing, even if you can't quite wrap your head around that,
is that this is being done for the sake of that person's salvation. Even this ultimate act of
throwing them out of the church is for that purpose. But so one of the effects of this though,
This understanding of both forgiveness being brought out by the community and this understanding.
of binding and of expionication. This is part and parcel of what the church does here in the
New Testament, right? And how forgiveness and expionation work is that the church has to have
definable borders. Yeah, you can't put someone outside of the church if there is no outside.
Right. If there's no border, right? So the church has to have a border.
there has to be church and not the church.
Right? And there has to be Christian and not a Christian. There has to be, right? There
has to be a border so that there can be this kind of understanding of church discipline.
Yeah. And I would say it's worth pointing out that no one in the scriptures or even in
the early church says, you know, I made a decision to become a Christian and so I became,
And so I am one, right?
And indeed you get like early church kin and sprints.
since talking about how to receive various kinds of heretics, whatever.
There's this line that's very memorable to me, which is, you know, on the first day,
we make them Christians.
Like, becoming a Christian is something that happens to you.
It's not something you sort of, you know, in my heart, I became a Christian,
which is not a meaningless thing to say.
I'm not saying that, but, but in terms of like your actual participation and membership
in the church, it's something that the community does to you.
Yeah.
So
And this may sound like I'm verging into picking on our
somewhat beleaguered after this episode Protestant friends
But I want to make clear
This isn't that because historically there is a Protestant ecclesiology
Right, there is a Protestant sense of the church that includes a church that has borders that includes
concepts of church discipline
Right?
And this particularly, particularly, if you read John Calvin, right?
This is for him, one of the marks of the true church, what makes a local church part
of the church for him is that there is church discipline.
Yeah.
Specifically talking about this element of excommunication, less on the forgiveness part.
I'll go too far into that.
Luther.
Marks of the Church are a little different. Luther also has a sacrament of
Absolution, so he kind of has a version of public confession sort of and
Some Lutherans still do still consider that a third sacrament some know but
But so they they had this this for an idea and this is where the idea of denominations comes from
Yeah
The idea was this is the Church of Christ,
denominee, whatever.
The Church of Christ, which is called Lutheran,
the Church of Christ, which is called reformed.
But from those traditional Protestant perspectives,
coming out of the Reformation,
there were groups that got together
and called themselves churches, but weren't churches.
There were false churches.
Yep.
There were three categories actually,
true churras of false church and a sect.
All right.
sex to be what you definitely didn't want to be, right?
That would be the equivalent today for most,
like from an American evangelical perspective, right?
The sect, the way it talked about it,
would probably the way a lot of American evangelicals
would look at like Mormons or Jehovah's Witnesses.
Yeah, they would probably use the word cult for that.
Right, they would use cult, they would say sect, right?
But so they had these categories and those categories have kind of honestly fallen away, at least in American evangelical practice.
Yeah.
And this is even true of a lot of people, at least publicly.
I don't know privately. I don't know confession. I don't think any confessions have been changed.
But publicly we get a lot of folks even
from Calvinist or Lutheran churches
who just there's only an invisible church,
it's just all the believers,
there are no borders, right, et cetera, et cetera.
And that creates a big problem
from the perspective of traditional Protestantism, right?
So, bluntly, if we went in the Tardis
that we got John Calvin in Geneva,
and
and brought him to the United States.
And he saw how Calvinist churches function
in the United States.
He would not think they were churches.
One reason would be the Eucharist,
but that's a whole other issue for another time.
The other, but the biggest issue would be
there's no church discipline
because the way things are now
in American evangelicalism is there can't be.
Yeah, I mean, because yeah.
Yeah, if you get thrown out of a particular local congregation.
and if you're serious about being a Christian,
you just go to some other one.
And down the block, down the block,
and the people in congregation A,
would not say that person is no longer a Christian.
Right, right, and they couldn't,
and they couldn't even say he's not a member of the church
because he's a member of a different church.
Right, right, now the street that they also acknowledge
is a true church, right?
So it can't functionally happen.
Yeah, new
rarely even gets to that thrown out level.
Yeah.
As soon as the pastor says something I don't like,
I could just go to the next church down the block
and it never even gets to that.
Yeah.
So there is no like discipline and authority structure,
at least for lay it in, there's more with clergy,
it depending, right?
And some Protestant domination.
Because the skin in the game is different.
Yeah.
But for a lay person, there's no church discipline.
So John Calvin would say that's not the church.
Yeah.
what are the marks of the true church? And so this is, this is, and it's progressed so far in the
United States that I've seen people complaining online. See, it is a critique of the Orthodox Church
or the Roman Catholic Church that we consider ourselves to be the Church.
and that someone who's excommunicated
is now not part of the church.
And it's not just, I don't have to go away
back in church history.
For John Calvin and Martin Luther,
that wasn't a bug, it was a feature of the church,
of the church.
And in case this still doesn't seem problematic
to some of our listeners,
Let me tell you about I will give a lot of
detail, but a leftist I know who's an atheist, right? Who is one of the people who
responded to and I'm not going down this culture war road, don't worry, but was
responding to the what is a woman question going around? It was basically
presented to him. Well, if you just say anyone who identifies as a woman is a
woman, then that makes the term woman meaningless. It doesn't mean anything
anymore right and his response.
His honest straightforward response, now he's an atheist, but was, no, being a woman
is like being a Christian.
Anyone who identifies as one is one.
Wow.
He said, but I wouldn't say that the term Christian is meaningless.
Yeah.
Right.
So, I hope folks find that troubling.
Right?
except that, and I think frankly,
We are at a point in American culture where the term Christian is meaningless.
I'll be blunt.
Doesn't mean we should stop using it, but...
No.
I'm not saying we should stop using it, but I've said it doesn't mean anything anymore, because
precisely for that reason, there's just anyone who calls themselves one is one, and there's
no way to say there's no border to it.
Yeah.
There's no way to say no you're not.
Right.
Right?
And there's no way to define it that would cover all those people.
So if I say, well, to be a Christian, you have to believe the contents of the
Nicene Creed. You'd be amazed how many people in American even
jelicos, and that leaves out because they're social trinitarians or any
number of other things, right? Or if you want to say, or if you go the other way,
you just say, well, anyone who loves and tries to follow the teachings of Christ
is a Christian that includes a lot of
of Muslims and Jewish people and Buddhists as Christians now.
Right? Like Muslims believe in the virgin birth. They believe Jesus was a prophet.
Right? But we wouldn't say they're Christians. Right? So yeah, it's really problematic on
the Americans.
seen. Right? And so in addition to calling people to kind of think about that, I
want to say to our Protestant friends that when you hear Orthodox people
refer to the Orthodox Church as the Church or the true Church or the visible
church, right? I think it would be helpful if instead of hearing a...
us trying to say something negative about you, right, which we're not, we're not trying
to say you're going to hell. We're not saying you're not really a Christian. We're not
saying any of that, right? That you would see that statement in this light, right? The
church as it is talked about in scripture has borders.
And rightly constituted, it has the ability to exercise church discipline.
And so, when we call ourselves the church or the true church, that's what we're trying
to do.
We're trying to reflect, biblically, historically, traditionally, the church is understanding
of itself.
Not to say anything about you, negative.
that's what we're attempting to say.
And as I said, 16th and 17th century Protestants
would not have had problems with us using that language.
No, I mean, right?
They might have disagreed with us.
Yeah, I mean, even most 90th century...
But there wasn't a problem with the language.
Even most 90th century Protestants, yes.
You know, like it's real,
you don't even have to go that far back
to have this sense of that each person
within his religious community believes that it's true
and that all others are there for it.
least somewhat false, maybe totally.
Yes.
Yeah.
So that's my appeal there.
And something we need to think about.
Because, and this isn't just our Protestant friends, right?
Because aroma Catholic friends and all of us Orthodox folks, we live in American culture
too.
Yeah, we're all affected by it.
Right?
this and you know
how even the term Christian now is used and heard in Britain, I guess it's a
little different. I guess in Britain Christian just means proper now.
I think so as complaints about that at some point. Your Christian name is just
your legal proper name.
So as a last note here, or a couple of notes, related notes here, there are a couple
things in the New Testament, where we are told that certain things that we can do are
means by which we receive forgiveness of sins from God. I phrased that the way I did on purpose.
This is not what to do to earn forgiveness. This is not right.
But these are things that we could do that will cause us to experience forgiveness of our
sins from God.
One of those that I know we talked about our previous episode is 1 Peter 4 verse 8.
Yep, which says, above all, keep loving one another earnestly, since love covers a multitude
of sins.
And so that covers language, is a tonement language, and we talked about it in that context
and 6 Cyprian's on Almsgiving, right.
Ray talks about how acts of love are means by which, towards others are means by which we experience the forgiveness of our own sins and our own failings.
Yep. And then another one, though, that's also important, comes once again from the epistle of St. James.
Yeah. So this is about, you know, if someone sees someone's sitting and then goes and brings them back. Right?
So that's immediate context. James 520.
Let him know, that's the person who's doing the retrieving, let him know that whoever brings back a sinner from his wandering
Will save his soul from death and will cover a multitude of sins the implication being there his own sins too
Right, right that that when you go out and someone is sending and you bring them back, right?
You bring the back to Christ you bring them back to repentance
right
That person experiences salvation.
right, and you experience the forgiveness of your own sins and being a part of the forgiveness of God that's brought to this, this person whom you're helping.
Notice also that we'll save his soul from death. This is another place where the verb save is used in the New Testament, not directly referring to God or to Christ.
Hmm. Yep. Right. That's you don't have to freak out about that.
Yes, just do a word search. There's actually a bunch
places. Yes, because we understand that that salvation is ultimately coming from God, but
that God works through people. Yeah. Yeah. So you can say, right? St. Paul can say, you know,
that he's all men, all things to all men so that by all means he might save some. He doesn't
mean he's saving them instead of Christ. Right. Yeah. Right. But he's saying I do this so that I can
be the instrument through which Christ.
saves some of these people.
So to wrap things up for this episode on confession, we ended up
talking a lot about ecclesiology.
That might be a little surprising.
You know, you turned on the episode and you probably didn't
think it would be about that.
But I think that ecclesiology is really, really important for us
to ponder particularly at this moment in our cultural history.
So what I mean is...
mean by that. Well, I think at least especially here in America, and maybe in other places in
the West too, I can't speak to that quite as well. Maybe other places in the world. But especially here
in our own country of America, people's isolation from each other has been increasing.
And, you know, we can blame social media, we can blame the pandemic.
We can blame a lot of things, but isolation, you know, things that you could track.
So for instance, people's participation in groups, right?
Whether it's church or, you know, the Rotary Club or, you know, whatever it might be, right?
People's participation in social activities has been going down for a long time actually,
a long time.
I think it's decades now.
It's been being tracked.
So while we could try to put the blame on uncertain things,
I think mainly we could just say that they haven't helped.
They've made it worse.
So we live in a time where isolation is increasing,
and a lot of people are suffering ill effects from that.
Mental health effects, definitely spiritual effects,
bodily health effects, you know.
There's a lot of suffering as a result of that.
And what exactly is it, please?
within that frame of this problem. Ecclesiology is how we are the church. It's
what it means for us to be the body of Christ. We've talked about some of our
earliest episodes, we're about God's body and how the church is Christ's body.
That is, the church is the collection of his powers, his abilities, his works in
in this world.
That he works through.
the church. And ecclesiology, therefore, in many ways, is the cure for this isolation and this
degradation that many of us are experiencing. And confession, in particular, as we saw,
especially here near the end of this episode, confession actually is a very ecclesiological
experience. On the one hand, the negative side,
there's a sense that you can, if you're unrepentant, you can find yourself outside the ecclesia,
outside the church. And now it's for the purpose of repentance, right? It's not like just get out.
We don't want you here anymore. But it's also for the purpose of protecting those who can be
potentially let us stray at the same time. So there's both things going on with that.
But also, you know, on the other side, confession is about healing. It's about that restitution,
about making things right about...
about repenting ever since. I mean, that's the program. That's the Christian life.
And it happens in relationship within the body of Christ.
There's a lot of people who are feeling very isolated, who certainly also do things like
praying alone at home and reading their Bible alone at home. And those are good things to do.
Right? But they cannot provide
The ecclesial logical dimension.
ecclesial dimension. They cannot provide churchliness because church is precisely a gathering. Church is precisely relationship
and as Father Stephen said earlier the experience of standing at home and saying to God, I did the following
versus having that experience in the church and having a priest standing next to you and you say, I did the
following, those are not the same experience. They're just not.
The second one calls you out of yourself in a way that the first one simply doesn't, right?
And it's not that God is not enough.
By no means would we ever say God is not enough, but we do know that God does work through
His body, the church.
We do know that God does work through other people.
And while we might be scared of that, right, I think for instance a lot of people have a
kind of, I don't know, a knee jerk anti-Roman Catholicism.
I think is what it comes down to, because of this sort of scary idea of clergy that
can stand between you and God.
We're not teaching that clergy or whoever stands between you and God.
There's nothing that can stand between you and God.
But when we fixate on that, then what we're doing is we're saying, you know what?
I don't need or want.
I don't want other people in my Christian life.
I don't want what God himself has provided.
I don't want the way that God is working through these other people.
I just want my own isolate experience.
When we do that, I mean, that's very, very destructive.
And we're letting our phobias, we're letting our fear of abuse get in the way
of using the good things that God has provided.
God has provided confession.
If we read it right there in the Bible, like we're not making this up.
It's right there in the scriptures.
God has given it.
and God has given
forgiveness of sins through confessing to other people. Does that mean that if
the other person says, well, I don't forgive you, then God says, well, I guess you
know, no, that's not what that means at all. But again, abuse does not prevent the
true use, right? So this is basic principle and Latin, abuse is non-tolateusum.
I'm sure I'm mispronouncing that.
But it is a basic principle.
that the abuse of something does not mean that the good use is no good. Right? We clean
up abuses, but we don't throw out the baby with the bath water. So it is a little scary.
All relationship is scary, but there are experiences, there's goodness, there's wholeness,
there's healing, as we see in scripture, there's forgiveness that's received only within
that context only within that context.
And so let's step outside of ourselves and let's go to confession.
Let's be a part of the body of Christ.
And let's not excommunicate ourselves.
Like, it sounds scary to be excommunicated, but if we're not participating in the body of Christ, we've excommunicated ourselves.
We did it to ourselves. That's the worst.
Right?
Let's step outside of that. Let's go.
show up. Let's go be the body of Christ together. And maybe if it's been a long time since you did it or maybe you had a bad experience, it's going to be uncomfortable.
Okay, I get that. I get that. But you don't let that rule. Don't let the wound become who you are.
Right? It's still the body of Christ. It's still the body of Christ. And that means we do this together.
And that means that we have
of access to this beautiful, beautiful, holy mystery of confession, of
absolution, of forgiveness of our sins. It's one of the most powerful experiences
that Christians can have. And there's only one context in which it really comes
to its fullness. So let's show up. Let's do the thing. Don't live in your
head.
Don't think that being a Christian is about stuff that you read or stuff that you think
or having the right opinions.
It's not.
Those can be important, but being Christian is about participation in the body of Christ
and confession is one of those key ways that we participate.
Father Stephen?
So as we mentioned, back when you're...
talking about the giving of the Torah originally. There are a lot of things that have been present
in the world since sin entered the world. Things like pain, suffering, shame, humiliation,
loneliness, emptiness, meaninglessness.
These things.
These have been out there.
Violence.
These are just facts of sinful human reality.
Those aren't the things that God brings into the world when He draws near to humanity.
Not am outside eye and definitely not in Christ.
said.
churches and I'm using churches here with a small C and in the loosest possible way, Christian
communities, right? So I'm including everybody, all our friends and a lot of Orthodox parishes too.
Have typically not done a great job of manifesting that fact to people.
So, we tend to fall into one of two pools.
People come into our church gatherings and all those things that they were already experiencing
out there in the world, like shame, isolation, embarrassment, humiliation, just feel exacerbated
to them.
They walk in the door and they feel judged and condemned.
or on the other side, on the flip side of the coin, they come in and they feel welcome
and find in the gathering, but that gathering doesn't present them any hope, any means of
change, any means of bettering their situation, sort of everyone commiserating.
expects any better out of any.
anybody else, but also there's no drive to do any better. There's no cure for the
meaninglessness. There's no cure for the shame. There's no cure for for any of these things.
And so the core of what we were talking about tonight, which is repentance and forgiveness,
that's a new thing that has come into the world. And that should be the earmarks of the
Christian community.
This should be what sets us apart, frankly, from every other organization or anything
else on Earth.
Is that this is the place where people can come to hear the words of life.
This is the place where people can come to find Christ.
This is the place where they'll find a path of repentance that will lead to forgiveness,
will lead to healing and freedom and transformation of their lives.
life. So on one hand, anybody who wants to can walk in the door, and on the other hand,
nobody is going to be just left the way they are when they first walk in the door, unless
they choose to turn around and leave themselves. Both not judging and condemning and calling to
repentance are possible at the same time.
Both
x.
experiencing forgiveness and taking sin seriously are possible at the same time.
Part of it that I think particularly in some of our Orthodox parishes,
we need to get more through our head is that joylessness is not a sign of holiness.
Say Paul says the exact opposite. He says joy is one of the fruit of the Spirit.
So if in your parish you're not experiencing joyfulness
the joy that comes from having your sins forgiven. The joy that comes from not having to be weighed
down by guilt and shame anymore. The joy that comes from knowing Christ. If you don't have that,
something is deeply wrong. It is deeply wrong. You can focus on repentance at the expense of forgiveness,
where it's all about being morose and morib-
about how sinful we are.
It's all about the way you feel walking into confession and not about the way you walk feeling, the way you feel walking out.
You should leave confession feeling 50 pounds lighter.
You should walk out with the knowledge that now you have been reconciled to
God in Christ
and that you're a process of reconciling with your brothers and sisters.
who are all supporting you in this.
People, if the church is a hospital and not a courtroom,
then we should all be happy that we're getting better
and recovering and being healed.
I don't think when Christ, as we read about in, say, Matthew's Gospel,
when he was out healing crowds of people
that the people who had been healed of ailments
that they'd sometimes had for years
We're walking away with a
grim look on their face. There was joy there. And so I think we need to kind of
refocus. We need to refocus as people and thereby help refocus our communities on
being communities that are about repentance and forgiveness. You don't know, I've
I've had a lot of conversations recently in various contexts with people
who aren't Christians, some of whom are atheists, and you do not know how much they long for.
Right? When I've told people who are atheists and don't know nothing about the Orthodox Church,
about forgiveness, festers. Where once a year we gathered together and asked each other for
forgiveness, for what we've done in the past year, how many of them tell me they long for something like
that. To be able
have an opportunity to just be honest with their friends and family about how they've been
and ask for their forgiveness and experience forgiveness because there's no forgiveness out there in the
world now. No one gets forgiven for anything. You get canceled, it gets brought up for the rest of
your life. Things will follow you for eternity and we've got a generation and a half now who almost
every moment of their life has been recorded on the internet, which means forever.
This is something only we have and only that we can only offer.
It's a kind of freedom that only comes through the Holy Spirit and through knowing Christ.
That's where our focus needs to be.
And when we do that, that's when what we have to offer the world is not moral principles
are theological principles, but the salvation that comes in Christ.
Amen.
Well, that is our show for today.
Thank you very much, everyone, for listening.
We weren't live this time, but God willing, we will be live next time, and we'd like to
hear from you.
You can email us at LordofSpirits at AncientFaith.com.
You can message us at our Facebook page, or you can also leave us a voicemail at SpeakPipe.com
slash LordofSpirits.
Or you can send a hate mail to Father Andrew Damon.
Yeah, I really like it.
and join us for our live broadcasts on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7pm Eastern 4pm Pacific.
And if you are on Facebook, like our page, join our discussion group, leave reviews and ratings, wherever it is you listen to this podcast.
But most importantly, please share this show with a friend who is going to benefit from it.
And finally be sure to go to www.inxionfaith.com, stroke support, and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
You have to say, Father, you act like you've got nothing to lose.
but I've already lost my patience.
Thank you.
Good night, and God bless you all.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits
with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I be held and I heard the voice of many angels
round about the throne and the beasts and the elders
And the number of them was 10,000 times...
times ten thousand and thousands of thousands,
seeing with a loud voice worthy as the land
that was slain to receive power and riches
and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.